Joseph McGirr, PhD

Evolutionary Biologist Postdoctoral Researcher

☐ email: josephmcgirr@gmail.com

twitter: @mcgirr_joewebsite: joemcgirr.github.io

github: @joemcgirr

Summary

I'm a bioinformatics scientist specializing in evolutionary genetics and population biology. I have a Ph.D. in biology from the University of North Carolina and have published research in genomics and transcriptomics in prominent journals including *Molecular Biology and Evolution, Evolution Letters*, and *Molecular Ecology*. My projects combine evolutionary theory with next generation sequencing data to answer questions at the intersection of basic and applied research.

Education

University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill 2015-2020 Ph.D. Biology
University of Colorado, Colorado Springs 2010-2014 B.S. Biology magna cum laude

Experience

2020 - Postdoctoral Researcher, Whitehead Lab, Dept. of Environmental Toxicology, University of California, Davis, CA

- Conducted temporal and spatial genomic contrasts to understand population collapse and recovery.
- Identified cross-species differential gene expression in response to osmotic stress.

2015-2020 PhD Student, Martin Lab, Dept. of Biology, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC

- Research on the genetic basis of adaptive traits and reproductive isolation in young species.
- Identification of novel candidate genes influencing craniofacial development.
- Discovered alleles under divergent selection contributing to gene misregulation in hybrids.
- Taught labs in evolution, animal behavior, anatomy, and course-based undergraduate research (CURE).

2011-2014 Undergraduate Research Assistant, Bono Lab, Dept. of Biology, University of Colorado, Colorado Springs, CO

- Research on early stages of speciation in Drosophila.

Selected Publications

full list at: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=BaXHXekAAAAJ&hl=en

Few fixed variants between trophic specialist pupfish species reveal candidate *cis*-regulatory alleles underlying rapid craniofacial divergence. McGirr JA and Martin CH. 2020. *Molecular Biology and Evolution*. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msaa218

Ecological divergence in sympatry causes gene misregulation in hybrids. McGirr JA and Martin CH. 2020. *Molecular Ecology*. https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.15512

Parallel evolution of gene expression between trophic specialists despite divergent genotypes and morphologies. McGirr JA and Martin CH. *Evolution Letters*. https://doi.org/10.1002/evl3.41

Funding and Awards

NSF-XSEDE Startup Allocation. 2020. \$2,000.

Triangle Center for Evolutionary Medicine Graduate Fellowship. 2018. \$10,500.

Rosemary Grant Travel Award, Society for the Study of Evolution. 2017. \$1,630.

L.I. Gilbert Travel Award, University of North Carolina Chapel Hill. 2017. \$750.

Skills

Code: R, python, bash.

Bioinformatics: Illumina whole genome and transcriptome alignment, annotation, and SNP calling with BWA, STAR, Trinity, GATK, samtools, ANGSD and R-Bioconductor packages.

• Control of the cont

Computing: SLURM, Amazon EC2, LSF, git. **Statistics:** Linear models, mixed models, classical

stats, GWAS, genetic demographic modeling. **Bench:** Designed and performed CRISPR/Cas9

gene editing experiments.